<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="0" Content_Hash="0">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000366f98</Id>
    <Library_Id>80a03482-cf8b-4055-82db-1aa09465d30f</Library_Id>
    <Title>Exception Information Disclosure</Title>
    <Category>Error Handling</Category>
    <Phase>NA</Phase>
    <Technology>ASP.NET</Technology>
    <Type>Vulnerability</Type>
    <DirectLink>Exception Information Disclosure</DirectLink>
    <Author />
    <Priority />
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="false" DataType="WikiText">
    <Data><![CDATA[==Description==

Exception Information Disclosure is a type of vulnerabilities where the application discloses information that somehow gives an advantage to the attacker as a result of an error. Attackers can use application error information to improve their ability to attack the application.

Almost all methods calls in computer programs, provide some feedback to the calling method about the status of the operation. This feedback could be a function return value, an exception which was thrown by the called method, or an error string. Based on this feedback, an applications decides if it should tell the user about a significant result (usually success or failure). When an error occurs, some applications choose to echo the internal error messages to the user. Though this feature is helpful in debugging a problem, it could lead to an information disclosure issue. An attacker could use this technical information to gain a better understanding about the back-end processing of the product and craft more malicious attacks against it.

==Countermeasures==

The following TeamMentor articles describe effective counter-measures against exception information disclosure vulnerabilities:

* [[Do Not Disclose Valuable Information in Error Messages]]
* [[Avoid Using Custom Error Pages to Denote Error States]]

==Checklists==

The following checklist items can help make sure that effective counter-measures against information disclosure vulnerabilities have been implemented:

* [[Valuable Information Is Not Disclosed in Error Messages]]
* [[Custom Error Pages Are Not Used to Denote Error States]]

==Additional Resources==

* For more information about exception information disclosure, please see https://www.owasp.org/index.php/Information_Leakage]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>