<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="0" Content_Hash="0">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>00000000-0000-0000-0000-00000090f889</Id>
    <Library_Id>b6f408c5-6e6e-4bc0-90a5-0bb10becc2ce</Library_Id>
    <Title>URL Handlers Are Not Used for Sensitive Operations</Title>
    <Category>Dangerous APIs</Category>
    <Phase>Implementation</Phase>
    <Technology>iOS</Technology>
    <Type>Checklist Item</Type>
    <DirectLink>URL Handlers Are Not Used for Sensitive Operations</DirectLink>
    <Author />
    <Priority />
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="false" DataType="WikiText">
    <Data><![CDATA[==What to Check For==

Verify that URL handlers are not used for sensitive operations.

==Why==

URL handlers may be abused in Cross-Site Scripting attacks. If URL handlers are used for sensitive operations, such sensitive operations may be exploited in Cross-Site Scripting attacks.

==How to Check==

To verify that URL handlers are not used for sensitive operations:

# **Identify all URL handlers used by the application.** Examine the application .plist file for //URL Types// defined by the application. These //URL Types// correspond to URL handlers used by the application.
# **Identify the operations associated with the URL handlers.** The developers should know what each //URL Type// is responsible for. 
# **Verify that URL handlers are not used for sensitive operations.** Examine each URL handler to decide whether it is safe to keep. 
# **Verify that URL handlers validate the origin of the URL request.** For URL handlers that are necessary for the application, make sure the //openURL// method is used.


==How to Fix==

To avoid using URL handlers for sensitive operations:

# **Identify all URL handlers used by the application.** Examine the application .plist file for //URL Types// defined by the application. These //URL Types// correspond to URL handlers used by the application.
# **Identify the operations associated with the URL handlers.** The developers should know what each //URL Type// is responsible for. Consider each one and decide if it is safe to keep.
# **Remove dangerous URL handlers.** Sometimes URL handlers are used for testing. Remove any URL handlers that may be too dangerous from the production release.
# **Verify the origin of the URL request**. Use the //openURL// method to make sure the URL request came from within the application itself or from a trusted application for any remaining URL handlers.

==Additional Resources==

* For more information about the //openURL// method, please see http://developer.apple.com/library/ios/#DOCUMENTATION/UIKit/Reference/UIApplication_Class/Reference/Reference.html]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>