<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="0" Content_Hash="0">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>00000000-0000-0000-0000-0000002a3f4d</Id>
    <Library_Id>b6f408c5-6e6e-4bc0-90a5-0bb10becc2ce</Library_Id>
    <Title>Authentication Is Implemented on the Server-side</Title>
    <Category>Authentication</Category>
    <Phase>Implementation</Phase>
    <Technology>iOS</Technology>
    <Type>Checklist Item</Type>
    <DirectLink>Authentication Is Implemented on the Server-side</DirectLink>
    <Author />
    <Priority />
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="false" DataType="WikiText">
    <Data><![CDATA[==Applies To==
* iOS applications that authenticate to a remote server.

==What to Check For==

Verify that authentication is implemented on the server-side.

==Why==

Server-side authentication should be used because client-side authentication is trivial to bypass.

==How to Check==

To verify that authentication is implemented on the server-side:

# **Review authentication requirements.** Consider the following aspects of authentication controls as pertaining to your application:
#* Enforcing password strength requirements.
#* Allowing secure password reset or recovery.
#* Requiring re-authentication for sensitive operations.
#* Using multi-factor authentication.
#* Using simple error messages that don't give away information to the attacker.
#* Using SSL/TLS to secure communications.
#* Throttling repeated authentication attempts.
#* Locking inactive authentication accounts.
# **Identify authentication code.** Identify the code that is responsible for authentication both on the iOS device and on the remote server.
# **Review authentication code.** Examine authentication code to find where the actual security controls are implemented.
# **Verify that authentication is implemented on the server.** Make sure that sufficient security controls to satisfy authentication requirements are implemented on the server-side.


==How to Fix==

To implement authentication on the server-side:

# **Define authentication requirements.** Consider the following aspects of authentication controls as pertaining to your application:
#* Enforcing password strength requirements.
#* Allowing secure password reset or recovery.
#* Requiring re-authentication for sensitive operations.
#* Using multi-factor authentication.
#* Using simple error messages that don't give away information to the attacker.
#* Using SSL/TLS to secure communications.
#* Throttling repeated authentication attempts.
#* Locking inactive authentication accounts.
# **Implement authentication on the server.** It is important to implement security controls, such as authentication on the server, because client-side security controls can be tampered with or disabled altogether on the client. Implement authentication controls that match the requirements defined in the previous step on the server back-end. 
# **Add client-side code that authenticates to the server.** Once authentication is implemented in accordance with the requirements, add client-side code that authenticates to the server. The client-side code will need an interface for managing authentication credentials, network code that communicates with the server using SSL/TLS, a token or some other means to maintain a session state on the server, and possibly secure storage for cached authentication credentials.

==Additional Resources==

* For more information about authentication requirements, please see https://www.owasp.org/index.php/Authentication_Cheat_Sheet]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>