<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="0" Content_Hash="0">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>00000000-0000-0000-0000-00000038e482</Id>
    <Library_Id>f798e6e6-1732-4172-9c47-9621d914efcd</Library_Id>
    <Title>Set the HTTPOnly and Secure Flags on Session Cookies</Title>
    <Category>Session Management</Category>
    <Phase>Implementation</Phase>
    <Technology> Any</Technology>
    <Type>Principle</Type>
    <DirectLink>Set the HTTPOnly and Secure Flags on Session Cookies</DirectLink>
    <Author />
    <Priority />
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="false" DataType="WikiText">
    <Data><![CDATA[==What to Do==

Set the //Secure// and //HTTPOnly// flags on all sensitive cookies, including session cookies.

==Why==

Set the //Secure// flag on all sensitive cookies to protect the contents of the sensitive cookies from eavesdropping attacks. Setting the //Secure// flag on sensitive cookies ensures they are only transferred over connections that are secured by SSL. 

Set the //HTTPOnly// flag on sensitive cookies to prevent the contents of those cookies from being access by Cross-Site Scripting exploits. The //HTTPOnly// flag prevents the contents of the marked cookie from being accessed by client-side script.

==How==

To set the //Secure// and //HTTPOnly// flags on all sensitive cookies:

# **Verify that SSL is available.** The //Secure// flag forces cookies to be sent over SSL. SSL has to be available for this to work.
# **Identify sensitive cookies.** Session cookies should always be considered sensitive. Enumerate all cookies used by the application. Make a list of cookies that may contain sensitive information.
# **Identify code that creates sensitive cookies.** For each sensitive cookie in the list, find the code that creates that cookie.
# **Set the //Secure// and //HTTPOnly// flags for each sensitive cookie.** For each piece of code that creates a sensitive cookie, add code that sets the //Secure// and //HTTPOnly// flags for the cookie. Make sure, that when the //Secure// attribute is set for a cookie, it is in response to a request that was made over HTTPS and not HTTP.
# **Configure the platform.** Many platform have configuration options that allow setting the //Secure// and //HTTPOnly// flags for session cookies. Please refer to your platform's documentation for information about whether this functionality is available and how to use it.]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>