<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="0" Content_Hash="0">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>00000000-0000-0000-0000-00000007e997</Id>
    <Library_Id>f798e6e6-1732-4172-9c47-9621d914efcd</Library_Id>
    <Title>Use Strong Cryptographic Algorithms</Title>
    <Category>Cryptography</Category>
    <Phase>Implementation</Phase>
    <Technology> Any</Technology>
    <Type>Guideline</Type>
    <DirectLink>Use Strong Cryptographic Algorithms</DirectLink>
    <Author />
    <Priority />
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="false" DataType="html">
    <Data><![CDATA[<h2>What to Do</h2>
  <p>Select a well-vetted algorithm that is currently considered to be strong by experts in the field, and select well-tested implementations. As with all cryptographic mechanisms, the source code should be available for analysis. For example, US government systems
 require FIPS 140-2 certification. When you use industry-approved techniques, you need to use them correctly. Don't cut corners by skipping resource-intensive steps (CWE-325). These steps are often essential for preventing common attacks.</p>
  <p>Do not develop your own cryptographic algorithms. They will likely be exposed to attacks that are well-understood by cryptographers. Reverse engineering techniques are mature. If your algorithm can be compromised if attackers find out how it works, then
 it is especially weak.</p>
  <h1>Why</h1>
  <p>As commercially available computing power rapidly increases and new threats emerge, it becomes more and more important to use strong cryptographic algorithms to secure sensitive data. Strong cryptographic algorithms assure that an attacker cannot break encryption
 in a timely manner.</p>
  <h1>When</h1>
  <p>Use this guideline whenever your application handles sensitive data.</p>
  <h1>How</h1>
  <p>Perform the following actions to encrypt sensitive data:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Identify sensitive data.</strong> Review your application design to determine what kinds of sensitive data your application handles.</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Choose cryptographic algorithms.</strong> Strong symmetric algorithms are AES and, to a lesser extent, 3-DES. Strong assymetric encryption algorithms are RSA, Elliptic Curve, and NTRU. The recommended key strengths are: 256-bit or more for AES, 3-DES
 key length is fixed at 168-bit, 1024-bit or more for RSA, 384-bit for Elliptic Curve cryptography, and 80-bit for NTRU.</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Choose libraries and APIs.</strong> Find libraries that implement your chosen cryptographic algorithms. In some cases, they may be implemented by the platform. Find out the APIs for using these algorithms.</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Implement encryption.</strong> Add functions to your applications that uses your chosen cryptographic APIs to encrypt and decrypt all the types of sensitive data that your application handles.</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Use encryption.</strong> Find code that handles sensitive data. Add code that calls your new encryption functions to encrypt and decrypt sensitive data as appropriate.</p>
    </li>
  </ol>]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>