<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="0" Content_Hash="0">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000371542</Id>
    <Library_Id>f798e6e6-1732-4172-9c47-9621d914efcd</Library_Id>
    <Title>Force Password Renewal</Title>
    <Category>Authentication</Category>
    <Phase>Implementation</Phase>
    <Technology> Any</Technology>
    <Type>Principle</Type>
    <DirectLink>Force Password Renewal</DirectLink>
    <Author />
    <Priority />
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="false" DataType="html">
    <Data><![CDATA[<h1>What to Do</h1>
  <p>Force users to renew their passwords after a given period of time.</p>
  <h1>Why</h1>
  <p>Forcing users to renew their passwords reduces the risk of valid credentials becoming exposed. While this technique can prevent attackers from obtaining the valid credentials through the use of a Brute Force Attack or a Dictionary Attack, it can also reduce the business risk associated with any instances of discovered or leaked valid credentials.</p>
  <h1>When</h1>
  <p>Your application should always force its users to change their passwords.</p>
  <h1>How</h1>
  <p>Use the following steps to force users to change their passwords:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Define a password change policy. </strong>Establish a maximum password age for your application's users. For example, require that users must change passwords every 60 days and privileged users must change passwords every 30 days. PCI DSS requirements state that a user's password must be renewed at most every 90 days and that the new password cannot be the same as the previous four.</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Design a password change mechanism.</strong> Track the password age and prompt the user to change their password when the password expires. For example, the following SQL transaction will help the application to determine whether a user's password has expired:</p>
      <pre>select * from passHistory<br />where userid = {{username}} and<br />last_changed &lt; (current_timestamp - interval '30' day);</pre>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Enforce the password change policy.</strong> Embed the change of password mechanism into the authentication routine. </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>(Optional) Check against previous hashed passwords to verify that passwords are not being repeated.</strong> One common password policy is to prevent users from using the same passwords repeatedly. To implement this, store the hashes of the previously used passwords and check the hashes of the new passwords against the stored ones.</p>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <ul>
  </ul>]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>