<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="0" Content_Hash="0">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000338bd6</Id>
    <Library_Id>f798e6e6-1732-4172-9c47-9621d914efcd</Library_Id>
    <Title>Centralize Authentication Controls</Title>
    <Category>Authentication</Category>
    <Phase>Design</Phase>
    <Technology> Any</Technology>
    <Type>Principle</Type>
    <DirectLink>Centralize Authentication Controls</DirectLink>
    <Author />
    <Priority />
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="false" DataType="html">
    <Data><![CDATA[<h1>What to Do</h1>
  <p>Centralize authentication controls.</p>
  <h1>Why</h1>
  <p>Implementing a single set of centralized authentication controls helps implement them correctly, use them correctly in the application, and manage them later on.</p>
  <h1>How</h1>
  <p>To centralize authentication controls:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Identify application requirements.</strong> Consider the following aspects of authentication controls:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Authentication should be required for all private pages. </li>
        <li>All password fields should be masked. </li>
        <li>Accounts should be locked after multiple failed authentication attempts. </li>
        <li>Authentication should be implemented on the server-side. </li>
        <li>Authentication controls should be centralized. </li>
        <li>Authentication controls should fail securely. </li>
        <li>Strong authentication credentials (passwords) should be enforced. </li>
        <li>Account management functions should be protected. </li>
        <li>User credential (password) changing functions should be protected. </li>
        <li>Re-authentication should be required for sensitive operations. </li>
        <li>Authentication credentials (passwords) should expire. </li>
        <li>Authentication events should be logged. </li>
        <li>Authentication attempts should be throttled. </li>
        <li>Passwords should be hashed and salted. </li>
        <li>Authentication credentials (connection strings) for external resources should be protected. </li>
        <li>Authentication with external services.</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Define authentication control APIs.</strong> Make the exposed APIs simple to use for developers. Define authentication APIs to satisfy all application requirements. Include functionality to authenticate with external services.</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Implement and document authentication controls. </strong>Implement and document authentication APIs to satisfy all application requirements. </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <strong>Use authentication controls in the application.</strong> Developers should use the centralized authentication controls whenever authentication is necessary.</p>
    </li>
  </ol>
  <h1>Additional Resources</h1>
  <ul>
    <li>For a discussion about how to throttle login attempts in PHP, please see <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2090910/how-can-i-throttle-user-login-attempts-in-php">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2090910/how-can-i-throttle-user-login-attempts-in-php</a></li>
  </ul>
  <ul>
  </ul>]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>