<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="0" Content_Hash="0">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>00000000-0000-0000-0000-00000008c774</Id>
    <Library_Id>f798e6e6-1732-4172-9c47-9621d914efcd</Library_Id>
    <Title>Get the Size of an Array Correctly</Title>
    <Category>Memory Management</Category>
    <Phase>Implementation</Phase>
    <Technology>Native Code</Technology>
    <Type>Guideline</Type>
    <DirectLink>Get the Size of an Array Correctly</DirectLink>
    <Author />
    <Priority />
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="false" DataType="html">
    <Data><![CDATA[<h1>What to Do</h1>
  <p>Calculate the amount of memory used by an array or a string correctly.</p>
  <h1>Why</h1>
  <p>Calculating the amount of memory used by an array or a string is very important when copying data to make sure that a sufficiently large buffer is allocated. Allocating a large enough buffer to fit data being copied is vital for preventing buffer overflows.</p>
  <h1>When</h1>
  <p>The amount of memory used by an array or a string should be calculated when copying data.</p>
  <h1>How</h1>
  <p>Use the<i> sizeof()</i> function to determine the size of an array. Do not pass a pointer as an argument to <i>sizeof()</i> when calculating the size of an array. When an array is passed to a function as a parameter, it is passed as a pointer. If that function then calls <i>sizeof()</i> using that pointer as an argument, <i>sizeof()</i> will return the size of the pointer, not the size of the array. To get the amount of memory used by an array or a string correctly, use <i>sizeof()</i> in the same scope in which the array or string is declared. Store the memory size of an array or a string as a variable and pass it as an argument to other functions when it is necessary to know the size of the array or string outside of the scope where it is declared.</p>
  <h1>Additional Resources</h1>
  <ul>
    <li>For more information about getting sizes of arrays correctly, please see "ARR01-CPP. Do not apply the sizeof operator to a pointer when taking the size of an array" at <a href="https://www.securecoding.cert.org/confluence/display/cplusplus/ARR01-CPP.+Do+not+apply+the+sizeof+operator+to+a+pointer+when+taking+the+size+of+an+array">https://www.securecoding.cert.org/confluence/display/cplusplus/ARR01-CPP.+Do+not+apply+the+sizeof+operator+to+a+pointer+when+taking+the+size+of+an+array</a></li>
  </ul>
  <ul>
  </ul>]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>