<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="98922925" Content_Hash="1987901431">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>eaeadcd7-9f67-4ce1-938e-1e7c6b02da65</Id>
    <Library_Id>4738d445-bc9b-456c-8b35-a35057596c16</Library_Id>
    <Title>The Anonymous Account Does Not Have Write Access to Web Content Directories And Cannot Execute Command-line Tools</Title>
    <Category>Server Hardening</Category>
    <Phase>Deployment</Phase>
    <Technology>ASP.NET 3.5</Technology>
    <Type>Checklist Item</Type>
    <DirectLink>The Anonymous Account Does Not Have Write Access to Web Content Directories And Cannot Execute Command-line Tools</DirectLink>
    <Tag />
    <Security_Demand />
    <Author />
    <Priority>J.D. Meier, Alex Mackman, Michael Dunner, Srinath Vasireddy, Ray Escamilla and Anandha Murukan</Priority>
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="true" DataType="Html">
    <Data><![CDATA[<h1>What to Check For</h1>
  <p>Check to ensure that the&amp;nbsp;anonymous account does not have write access to Web content directories and cannot execute command-line tools because attackers target this well known account to perform malicious actions.</p>
  <h1>How to Fix</h1>
  <p>To secure the anonymous account: </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <strong>Deny write access to Web content directories</strong>.
<p>Make sure that it is not possible for this account to write to content directories, for example, to deface Web sites.
</p></li>
    <li>
      <strong>Restrict access to System tools</strong>.
<p>In particular, restrict access to command-line tools located in \WINNT\System32.
</p></li>
    <li>
      <strong>Assign permissions to groups instead of individual accounts</strong>.
<p>Assigning users to groups and applying permissions to groups instead of individual accounts is good practice. For the anonymous account, create a group and add the anonymous account to it and then explicitly deny access to the group for key directories and
 files. Assigning permissions to a group allows you to more easily change the anonymous account or create additional anonymous accounts because you do not need to recreate the permissions.
</p><blockquote><strong>Note</strong>&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;IISLockdown denies write access to content directories for the anonymous account by applying a deny write access control entry (ACE) for the Web Anonymous Users and Web Applications groups. It also adds a deny execute ACL
 on command-line tools.</blockquote></li>
    <li>
      <strong>Use separate accounts for separate applications</strong>.
<p>If your Web server hosts multiple applications, use a separate anonymous account for each application. Add the accounts to an anonymous Web users group, for example, the
<strong>Web Anonymous Users</strong> group created by IISLockdown, and then configure NTFS permissions using this group.
</p><p>For more information about using multiple anonymous accounts and hosting multiple applications, see Chapter 20, "<a href="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa302436.aspx">Hosting Multiple ASP.NET Applications</a>."
</p></li>
  </ul>
  <hr />
  <p>Adapted from Microsoft patterns &amp; practices guidance.</p>]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>